吾爱
My own darling,
有一天我将与你再度共眠 我保证
one day I shall lie with you again, I promise.
届时我们将永不分离
And we shall sleep together for eternity.
(伦敦 1538年)
让开 伙计
Get out of the way,fellow.
抱歉 阁下 您要过去？
Sorry Sir, would you try to pass.
当然了 快点
Of cause I'm trying to pass,quickly now...
不说别的 阁下
before I know anything Sir.
您是罗伯特·帕金顿先生吧
You are Mr. Robert Packington, Sir.
议员大人 掌玺大臣的朋友
Member of paliament, friend of Lord Privy Seal.
是吗 阁下
Is that right? Sir.?
是的 千真万确
Yes, at all counts
请让开吧 谢谢啦
by thank you again, step aside.
您着急赶路吗 阁下
Aim't you in a hurry, Sir.
对极了
Yes, I am.
不必了
No need.
你赶着上黄泉路吧
This is what you are hurrying.
- 抓到凶手了吗？- 没有 大人
- Have you caught the villain? - No, my lord
他从齐普赛街逃脱了 警卫官四处都派了人
He has run off the cheapside, the Sergeant-at-Arms has his man all over the area.
设法抓住他吧
Pray god to catch him,
我相信帕金顿先生不过是个无辜的牺牲品
but I'm sure Mr. Packington in every way innocent victim.
那他因何被刺
Then why he is killed
估计是要给我传递个信息 我不乏敌人 累斯莱先生
assumed to send a msg to me,I'm not short of enemies,Mr.Risley
最难的事情莫过於推行新举措
there is nothing more difficult to carry out into a new order things
那么您认为加德纳主教是幕后黑手
then you think Bishop Gardiner might be behind this
还是沙福克公爵大人
or my lord Suffolk.
我不妄自推测
I'm not speculated.
不如说宫廷内外暗潮涌动
But I'll say There are dark forces of work of inside and outside the court.
必须除掉
They must be defeated.
但要万分谨慎在确定到底是何许人也
must be careful not act until we completely sure who they are,
其目的何在之前不能贸然行事
what they want
同时我已着手给国王找个新娘
and mean time I've set to work for a new bride for the King
虽然已经有了一个王嗣 不过
it's true we have the heir at last,but alas,one is scarely sufficient
一个远远不足 一定得再生个儿子以策安全
to be safe, he must produce another
国王怎么样了
how is the King
他自闭了 有人说他伤心 其实已经完全崩溃
he shut himself away, some say for grief, but he is all broken
除了一个人外 他摒弃了所有仆役
have none attendantman,but only one
那是谁？
who is that
陛下
Majesty
你怎么想
well,what do you think
我从来不想 你疯了吗
I don't think, are you mad
"想"很危险
thinking is dangerous
不过我会眨眼
but I'll wink
傻瓜
idiot
什么 那么你呢 想想看
what, what about you, think about it
你找到了个完美老婆 她甜美温良 丰乳美胸
you found the perfect wife, she is sweet,pliable,she even have good tette
除此之外 她还给你生了渴望已久的儿子
on top of that she gave you the son that you always wanted
你却居然让眼睁睁让她死掉了
and you let her died.
看在上帝的份上 你却认为我是傻瓜
Jesus Christ Mercy, you think I'm idiot
而且还不仅仅她一个
and she is not the only one
可怜被抛弃的凯瑟琳
poor, abandoned Catherine
小心你说的话
careful...
还有一个就不说名字了
and there is other one who's name escaped me,
因为她的脑袋都没了 都丢了 都丢了
as her head escaped her, all lost, all lost
下地狱吧
Go to Hell.
下地狱？我想我已经到了
Well, go there, I thought I already arrived.
我的陛下 这就是地狱
For surely gracious Lord, this is hell
可怜 从来不知其母亲何人
poor lad, never to know his own mother.
不 他会知道 会通过我
No, he will know her, through me
通过所有了解他母亲善良贤淑其他人
through others who knew her gentle kindness
我们都将牢记她 使她的精神永远陪着他成长
we shall all keep her memory so grim he will always think her spirit.
等他首次听说她时 她还会那么年轻
And she is still so young and fair when he first hears talks to her
王后的侍从业已遣散
My Lady's household is now to be dissolved.
国王虽然在王后去世之后十分悲伤 但他依然下令
The king himself seems very grief by her death, but he has commanded
必须动用一切力量保护他的宝贝独子
that no efferts be spear to protect this precious jewel his only son
将在汉普顿宫为他特设一处新居所 我也即将前往该处
A new household to be established for at Hampton Court and I'm aheaded.
全面负责他的生活起居和教育
Responseful all together for his nutrition and education
我想您是他的不二之选 布赖恩女士
I can think of no one who could be trusted more, Lady Bryan
也许不久的将来 上帝也会令玛丽女士您添子
Perhaps someday soon God will let Lady Mary you yourself have a child
传说是西班牙王子
I hear some rumors of Spanish prince
是的 不过世事无常
Yes, but there is nothing definite
同时我该打道回我的杭斯顿宫
and at the meantime I shall return to Hunsdon and live quitely
如同英格兰其它淑女一样在乡郊安静度日
in countryside like a English gentlewoman
不过我须带伊丽莎白女士与我同行
except that I shall take the Lady Elizabeth with me
你该知道哪位小女士从不安静
I know that youg lady you should no quite at all
我不介意
I don't mind
她和我兄弟爱德华
she and my brother Edward are,
是除了国王之外的所有家人 我会全然热爱他们
excepting the King,my only family, and I should love them all
噢 忘了一件事 您的儿子弗朗西斯爵士近来如何
Oh, I have forgotten, how is your son, Sir Francis?
他出门为国王办事去了吗
Has he now gone away for the King?
是的 女士 唉 我也没有他的消息
He has, My Lady,but, alas, I have no news of him.
(意大利 卡塞塔)
弗朗西斯爵士 我来对您光临卡塞塔表示欢迎
Sir Francis, I come to show welcome you to Caserta
你们离开
leave
可以给我出示一下您的通行文件吗
May I see you letter of passage
这些是给那不勒斯王公的介绍信
these are the letters of introduction to the prince of Naples
你不相信我
you don't trust me
我需要查验那些信件
I need to see those letters
而我需要见波尔红衣主教
and I need to see Cardinal Pole
难道您认为您能威胁到我吗 弗朗西斯爵士
Do you really suppose you can threaten me, Sir. Francis.
[意大利语]门被锁住了
La porta e' bloccata!
- 开门 把门打开 - [意大利语]把门打开
- Aprite! Aprite la porta! - Aprite la porta!
告诉我那个叛徒在哪儿 我想要知道他在哪儿
Now tell me where is the traitor,I want to know where he is
你得要告诉我 否则向上帝起誓 我一定会杀了你
and you are going to tell me, or God help me,I'll kill you
而我却有豁免权
and I have the immunity to do it.
现在告诉我 他在这里吗
So tell, is he here
他在这里吗 他到底在哪儿
is he here, where is he
这叫做"无双宫"
it is called nonsuch palace.
为啥
Why?
因为它不存在吗
Because it does't exist.
不
No
是因为独一无二
Because this is no place like it
那还不就是不存在
for itself exist.
我会去建它
I will built it
那么你是要建一个虚幻的宫殿
then you will built an imaginary palace
然后你会需要一些虚幻的人物去进驻
and you will need imaginary people to fill it
那不是很多吗
are there not a lot of them
我是这么想的 你是一个 我也算是一个
I think so, for you, a one,and I, another
还有整个宫廷都如同大梦一场
and whole court imagine to me in all of this the dream
这是我所仅有的一切
it's all I have
那就继续在梦中吧
then dream on
晚安 波尔红衣主教大人
Good Night, Cardinal Pole
等等 等等
wait,wait,
看来我杯弓蛇影
for gradual I afraid of my own shadow
这是教皇玺封 圣父亲自赐福于我
the Papal Seal, Holy Father bless it himself
当我拥有之后就感觉安全些
I felt safe when I have it
你能在门边睡觉吗
will you sleep beside the door
遵命 主教殿下
Yes, Your Eminence
- 好吧 - 晚安 主教殿下
- fine then. - Good night Eminence
咻 不许动
shhh, don't move
叛徒
Traitor
他逃了
He's got away
亲爱的
sweet heart
出什么事了吗
what's wrong with you
是的
yes
不 有时我在想不该要这个孩子
no,for sometime I think I donot want this child in my belly
噢 亲爱的 何出此言
oh my love, why do you say so
因为会总是被其他孩子的鬼魂纠缠着
for he will always be hunted by ghost of other children
被谋杀的那些孩子 不该杀的
murdured childrem,unwanted
未被宠爱的 遍被血腥记忆所驱使的孩子们
unloved, for the bloody memory provoked
如果能在孩子诞生之前就丢了就再好不过了
better was gone before he was ever born
对于无双宫我另发奇想
I have other ideas for the palace
我要建美丽的花园
I will construct beautiful gardens
满是各种奇花异草与小树林 峡谷掩藏 曲径通幽
full of groves, hidden dells,paths
要雕塑美丽的黛安娜女神沐浴像
there will built grove of Diana,showing Godness on bath
到处是雕像 喷水池水花四溅
statue every where, fountains, spatting water
花瓶 大理石鸟像
vase, Marble birds.
从大理石鸟嘴喷水
Pour fall water from these bills.
你认为怎样 傻子
What would you say,fool?
我都喜欢 喜欢这一切
I like it at all, I like everything about it
除了小树林 我不喜欢小树林
except the groves, I don't like the groves
其他的所有的喷水池 小道
all the fountains,all the paths
那些大理石鸟等其他的一切我都喜欢
all the marble birds,everything else I like
你根本不理解
you don't understand
法国国王 有了让世人都羡慕嫉妒的香波堡
the French King,has the palace Chambord which is the envy of all world
但是无双宫 将要胜过它千万倍
but Nonsuch, would trump it a hundred, a thousand times
那么 总有一天
then,in time,
和其他东西一样 一切都将灰飞烟灭
like everything else, it will dissolve away
就像古罗马的废墟和罗德岛巨像
like the ruins fo the ancient Rome, like Colossus of Rhodes
所有的一切终将变成废墟
all things tends towards their ruins
即使是你这等傻人建造过最伟大的宫殿
even great houses of fools shall built them
只有一个小小的空间
and so in a litlle space
说明无双宫的确存在过 消失过
there indeed be Nonsuch places, frame all be gone
繁华皆去不复返 白云千载空悠悠
a vacancy,a nullity, a green thought in a green shade
即便如此 人们也会说
and yet, people would say,
此地曾经有过伟大的宫殿
there once exist a great palace there
一个美奂美仑 无与伦比的宫殿
a palace beyond beauty, a palace beyond compare
而那是亨利国王所建
and King Henry built it
那将万古流传
that is still exist.
是的 那倒是真的 唯一能够留下的就只在人们的心中
True,true, the only thing which shall exist in people's head
自古佳思难追寻 未曾把握已渺去
and you never find a hatch of fine, because you could make it fly
该你了
your turn
- 别装傻 - 干嘛不
- don't play the fool.- why not
你会输的
you'll lose the game
是的 不过我宁可输牌 也不想输掉脑袋
indeed,but I'll much rather lose the game than lose my head
蠢货
fool
卡文 你来晚了 你西摩主子知道吗
Gawen!You are late, does your master Seymour know
你怕什么
what do you scare of?
可怜的卡文
Poor Gawen!
这是何人
Who is he?
这是格文·凯鲁 西摩大人的扈从之一
Sir Gawen Carew. One of Lord Seymour's retainers
为何被杀
why has he killed?
可能是赌博纠纷吧 大人
It may have been for gamblin debit, my Lord.
可能？
May
我们还在调查当中 大人
We are investigating,my Lord.
还未发现凶手
You have not found the killer?
尚未 大人 我们仅知可能是苏塞克斯大人的扈从所为
No, my lord. Although it seems possibly one of my Lord Sussex retainers
在王宫内国王居所处持有武器是非法的 须加以严惩
its illegal to carrying arms in court while the King residence, the penalty is SEVERE
遵命 大人
Yes, My Lord
关于我的朋友帕金顿那件案子 找到凶手没
what about my friend, Mr.Packington? have you found the killer?
没有 大人
No, My Lord
没有
No, eh?
在我看来 警官 你被任命掌管王宫秩序
It seems to me, Sergeant, that you are the man pointed keep order in court
你却严重疏于职守
you are singularly fail you duties.
我相信你能设法捉拿凶手 防止暴力事件再度发生
I trust you now can prehensile the villain and prevent the further viololenc
否则你须为你的玩忽职守付出代价
otherwise you will pay the price of your failures.
这是命令
It is an order.
- 您可带弗朗西斯爵士通过 布赖恩女士 - 谢谢
- You can take Sir Francis through, Lady Bryan. - thank you
- 这边走 弗朗西斯 - 妈妈先请
- This way, Francis, - Mama
这是作甚
what's this
国王亲自下令
The King gave order personally that all the rooms and chamber
所有在王子居处周边的房间走廊
and passages arround prince's apartments
必须每日以肥皂水刷洗三次
must be scrubed with soap three times daily
王子也拥有自己单独的厨房为其备餐
The Prince also own a kitchen for all his meal prepared has **win for mother Jack
所可能接触的一切必须重新清洗
Everything he might touch to be washed
所吃的一切必须尝毒
Everything he might eat tasted for poison
他的私人侍从监督他的食物 他的房间 每日洗漱
His personal Chamberlain supervising his meal, his room his daily bath
他一定是全英格兰最干净的婴儿
He must be the cleanest baby in England.
他是全英格兰最宝贝的婴儿
He is the most precious baby in England.
勋爵大人
My lord
有劳了 布赖恩女士
Thank you, Lady Bryan.
你来此作甚 难道国王因为你让波尔神父
Why have you come here? Has The King banished you to the nursery
从你指尖逃脱就罚你来给王子负责生活起居
for letting Cardinal Pole sliped to your fingers ?
陛下想确定他的儿子一切安好无恙
His Majesty is anxious to assure to himself how's his son well-being
不劳烦心
He has no need to be concerned
保护王子乃是我的第一要务
the protection of the Prince is also my first priority,
因为他也是我的血亲
since he is also my blood.
如果将来弗兰西斯爵士不来打扰我的外甥我将不胜感激
I will thank you Sir Francis in future to leave my nephew alone
还有我的太太 我说的够清楚吗
And my wife too,do I make myself clear?
大法官大人驾到
The Lord Chancellor
瑞奇 请坐
ah, Richie,please take a seat
有新事务要和你协商
There is something new I would like to discuss with you.
你当然知道国王要求重新装潢宫殿
You know of cause the King has informed us to modernize
包括扩建汉普顿宫
his palace including enlargement of Hampton Court
大人 我已经授权支付了该工程款项
My Lord, I have alreayd released fonds for the project
还有建设圣詹姆斯宫的款项
and also for the construction of St James Palace.
这里还有个新的
well, there is a new one.
这真是个梦幻工程
This is a Fantasy work
这将耗资不菲
It will cost a fortune
解散修道院的结果已经使国王收入颇丰
As result of dissolution of monastries His Majesty has gained a large fortune
虽然如此 但恐怕负担不起梦幻工程的挥霍
Yes, Did you ever supposed it will squander on fantasies
你是否能…
can you not
说服他
talk to him
瑞奇 国王的愿望就是命令
Richie,the King's will is the King must have
无法争辩 何况他还沉浸于丧失爱妻的悲痛之中
It's not to be arguable with him on crisis he is still mourning his dead beloved wife.
我无法和他交谈 除了威尔·萨默斯
He is unable to talk to no one but Will Somers.
威尔·萨默斯
Will Somers?
他是个傻子啊
He is a fool?
他不跟任何人说话 除了这个傻子？
He will talk to no one but his fool
这不是第一次了
it's not the first time.
总是那么不同寻常
Extreme always.
会持续到何时？
For how long.
我不知道
I don't know.
我真希望在他缺席的情况下能度过难关 否则就下地狱
But I wish to come out without him, or we will be gone to hell
好了 傻子 我们还需要决定一些其他事情
now fool,there are something else we have to decide
我们得决定对我们的新教会和我们的臣民来说
we have to decide which articles are faith and which commandments are best
采用哪些教义信条 哪些诫命最好
for our new church,our people
以便他们走入正路
so they can walk in good ways.
"不可… "什么呢？
"Thou shalt not " what?
做傻瓜？
Play the fool,
"(不许)搞邻人的妻子"
(Thou shalt not) cover their neighbours' wife.
… 除非她很漂亮
...Unles she is very pretty.
"也不许搞男仆 婢女 或与牛驴兽交"
Or he is man servant, maid servant, ox, ass,
或者你家邻居老婆的屁股
or your neighbour's wife's ass.
别太过分了 傻子
don't be supercilious fool .
你知道吗 你知道吗
Did you know, did you know,
哪些道德规范 有613款诫命之多
there is ethics, there are 613 in commandments.|.
"行邪术的女人 不可容她存活"
Thou shalt not suffer a witch to live,
"一年三次 你要向我守节"
thou shalt have 3 feast days onto me a year.
"不可亏负寄居的"
Thou shalt neither vex a stranger
"凡与兽淫合的 总要把他治死"
Whosoever lieth with a beast shall surely be put to death
与绵羊交 与鸽子配
Sheep shaggs, Pigeon fanciers.
"不可对罗马教士不敬"
Thou shalt not venerate the vicar of Rome,
都是些扯蛋的借口
all of excuse of ass
"因为国度是祢的"
For thine is the kingdom,
"权柄和荣耀也是祢的"
The power and glory
阿门
amen
那是主祷文
That's the doxology.
主祷文
Doxology.
那是猪屌文
It's the dog's bloody bullet.
我很想她 我太想她了
I miss her so well. I miss her so much.
我知道 但陛下必须节哀顺便
I know, but this is you should pass .
何苦总是沉浸于悲伤之阴霾
Why go on dwelling in darkness.
你该知道有个伤心国王的土地如同久旱的废田
You know that the land has wounded king is only a parched wasteland
渴求雨露滋润与陛下的恩典
thirsting for rain and your Majesty's grace.
长官 有打斗发生 您快去瞧瞧吧
Sir, there is a fight. You'd best come quick.
全部住手
Whoever you are, Hold,
我以国王之名命令你们立刻放下剑 否则以叛国论处
put off your swords in the name of the king, you are coming in traitor,
你 放下剑
you sir, get off your sword,
违者格杀勿论
I say on pain of death, give them up.
- 行了吧 警官 - 把剑交出来
- you have it, sergeant, - give me your sword.
好吧
Very well.
快 快去
Go. go out, go
即使陛下圣体欠安
Although the king is indisposed,
任何臣工也无权僭越行事
no one has the authority to make decision on his behalf.
我乃当朝国舅 皇位继承人的监护人
The prince, my nephew, is in my custody,
没有我的允许任何人无权探望王子
and no one is or will be allowed to see him without my written approval.
王子乃陛下之子国之瑰宝 而非你私人物品
He is the king's son and property of the state. He is not your property, my lord.
掌玺大臣驾到
Lord privy seal.
勋爵大人们
My lords.
公爵大人
Your Grace.
我诚请各位维护朝政之秩序
I beg you can we not now come to order.
秘书大人 您有何权召集国王陛下之议会成员
By what right and by whose command Mr. secretary, you summon the king's council?
荷西大人 您该知道陛下现在无法上朝理政
My lord Hussey, as you well know the king is incommunicado.
所以您就有权将自己凌驾于朝堂之上了吗
Then you are only authority to put yourself above other as you usurped one.
身为掌玺大臣
As a lord privy seal, I think I have the right and the responsibility
我想我有权也有责任召集各位大人们商议国是
and legal pretence of summoning your lordship's council.
各位大人 显然现在必须在陛下缺席的情况下
Gentlemen, gentlemen. Surely you can see there must be a meeting of council
召集议会商议宫中多起恶性暴力事件时有发生
in the absence of the king has been malevolence violence at court
包括如今警卫官被杀一事
including now the death of the Sergeant-at-Arms
我听闻此事您的侍从深涉其中 秘书大人
I've heard you own servant so much involved in the violence, Mr. Secretary.
有人称事情就是他们挑起的
Some say they may have even provoked it.
若是可以证实 显然我会丧失公爵大人之信任
If that can be proved, I shall rightly forfeit your lordship's trust.
但我想大人您保证传言非实 而另有他人需扪心自问
But I can assure your grace it is not true and others should look to their own conscience.
你什么意思
What do you mean by that?
我说有人为了一己私利
I mean there are some desire disorder with their all heart
制造混乱来混水摸鱼
thinking to use it to their own advantage.
克伦威尔你太不自量你的出身和等级
Mr. Cromwell you presume too far above you very base and low degree.
除了陛下 你没有任何权利召唤我
To the king his will, you will not summon me to any more to anything.
甚至是为这种狗奴才打架的小事召唤我
Not even to a dog fight.
看在上帝的份上 您知道陛下的近况吗
For god's sake, have you any news of the king?
是的 陛下正在重写主祷文
Yes, he is. We is rewriting the Lord's Prayer
和十诫
and the Ten Commandments.
- 什么 - 确实如此
- What? - Certain.
- 对虾如何 - 美味至极
- How the prawns? - Delicious.
我已警告弗朗西斯爵士离你远点
I've warned Sir Francis Bryan to stay away from you.
为何
Why?
这样很危险
It's dangerous.
对你没危险 也不会怀上小孩
Will not to you, surely nor will the boy.
国王偏信他 这对任何人都危险
The king listens to him, that means dangerous to everyone.
我会叫他万劫不复的
I shall have to destroy him.
可惜了 他能取悦妾身呢
What a pity! He makes me laugh.
我确信他取悦很多女人
I'm sure he makes a lot of women laugh.
爱德华 这对你不过是件小事而已
It's a very small thing to you isn't it, Edward?
相对诸多要事来说 是的
I think there are more important things, yes.
夫君所言甚是
No doubt you're right.
但夫君的所作所为已令妾身无法忠于您了
But as long as you do, don't expect me to be faithful to you.
再来点对虾
May I have some more prawns?
醒醒 醒醒
Waking, waking!
陛下宣您觐见
His Majesty would like to see you.
即刻
at Once.
克伦威尔大人 陛下
Master Cromwell. Majesty.
朝上政务如何
How it goes the world?
法王致函恭贺陛下喜得嗣子
The King Francis has written to your Majesty to congratulate you on your birth of your son.
告诉法王 寡人的这份喜悦中式夹杂着无限悲痛的
Tell Francis. Divine providences mingle my joy with bitterness of death,
因为爱妻的仙逝
of her who brought me such happiness.
宣加德纳大主教觐见
Tell Bishop Gardiner, I wish to see him.
我有事召见他 是 臣遵旨
I wish to talk to him. Of course, your Majesty.
王子如何 遵照陛下严旨
How is my son? Everything has been done to protect the prince
王子殿下已经得到了无微不至的保护
in strict accordance with your Majesty's instructions.
寡人深爱吾儿
I love that boy.
切勿在他身上发生任何事
If anything should ever happen to him.
陛下臣不得不启奏 启奏何事
Majesty I wonder. Wonder?
但说无妨
Tell me.
克伦威尔大人所请何事
What do you wonder? Mr. Cromwell.
臣乞陛下考虑另立新后之事
I wonder if your Majesty can frame your mind towards a new marriage.
至少 是为保护嗣子着想
After all, however much is done to protect the prince?
朕会考虑的 为何不呢
I may frame my mind, why not?
何人可为备位中宫之人选呢
What do you suggest?
臣已通知在法国
I took the liberty of instructing our ambassadors in France
及其它公国的我国使节开始征求
and in Low Countries to begin making inquiries.
继续
And?
法国提议了两名闺秀为陛下之王后人选
The French have proposed two possible consorts for your Majesty,
一位是法王之女玛格丽特公主殿下
Margret, the daughter of the king,
另一位是吉斯公爵千金玛丽小姐
and Marie, the daughter of the Duke Guise.
法国公使更称赞后者
Our Ambassador of France sings the latter's praises
虽然她有可能与苏格兰王已有婚约
although it seems she is half promised to the king of Scottland
陛下
Majesty.
国王怎么样了
How is the king?
陛下刚结束隐居生活
He has just lately emerged from his seclusion.
传闻他贵体欠安
It is said that although he is a little indisposed,
朝臣们都在期待他另立新后
the council has urged him to take extreme steps of marrying him.
另立新后
Marriage?
不知你是否在我与路易斯大公的联姻方面有何进展
I don't suppose if you've had done any more about Don Louise of my own marriage.
在此方面 公主 我并没有新的消息要启奏
As to that, Lady Mary, I'm afraid I have no news for you,
无论是好的或是坏的
whether good or bad.
看来此桩婚事束之高阁 至少目前看来这样
It seems perhaps the issue is in suspense at least for the time being.
也许我的宿命就没有婚姻
Perhaps it's my fates not to marry.
不 公主
No, gentle lady. No,
我相信陛下会决心给你安排一桩最佳姻缘
I'm sure the king will make up his mind to arrange a most brilliant marriage for you.
如果不是路易斯殿下 或许某位更佳人选
If not to Don Louise, then to someone even more elegance
我想你曾说过路易斯殿下无与伦比
I thought you said Don Louise is incomparable.
女士 并非是说…
Madam I did not mean.
您说的很清楚了
You meant well,
您总是怀着好意
you always mean well.
珍的侍从现在都要遣散
Jane's household now is broke up
你打算去哪儿 米赛尔登女士
where you will go Lady Misseldon
去和我母亲生活在一起
Live with my mother
那么你订婚的那个年轻人怎样呢
what about the young man you were engaged to
罗伯特·泰维斯托克爵士
Sir Robert Tavistock
我想他对我不甚感兴趣
I think he is not so interested in me.
那他就太傻了
He is the fool then.
何出此言 弗朗西斯爵士
What's kind think, Sir Francis.
如果他悔婚的话那他就太傻了
He is so foolish that he turned down your peerage
岂不知你会获得贵族封号
and gifts of one of dissoved abbeys.
和被赐予被遣散的修道院中的一个
If he regrets to marry you
陛下 如果他因这笔财产而爱我那我会更不想他
Majesty, I would think less him if he intends such gift in order to love to me.
陛下你一直无比慷慨大度
Your Majesty have been more than generous and gracious ,
但我注定要回家去 看他是否会自动找上门的
but I'll settle my plan to go home, to see what if he will come to me
以我目前的心境 你这番话弥足珍贵
in my present state of mind,you could not said more admiralbe thing
你可带着我的祝福离去
You may leave with all our love and blessing.
再多一夜
one more night.
叛徒波尔从你手心逃脱了
the traitor Pole escaped to you.
是的 我派了些特务在搜寻他 但他已偷偷潜回意大利
yes, there's other agents looking for him. But he was smuggling to Italy.
无疑现在会受到教皇的重重保护
No doubt he is seated on the Pope lap even now.
他的叛变伤透我的心
His betrayal hurts to me.
但是他很愚蠢 无法抓住一个可恨的波尔
but he is idoit, that fauling one bring sick Pole,
他却会导致其整个伟大家族的毁灭
what say better wickless fool he will be ruin of so great family
虽然我无法抓到他 我发誓我将咬碎他的心
Though I cannot touch him, I swear I will eat his heart.
(意大利 罗马)
圣父在今天的祈祷提到了你
Our Holy father mentioned you in his prayers today
他感谢上帝让你安全返回
He thanks to God for your safe delivered
我想我活不了多久了
I was sure I'm going to die.
你的死期远远未到
No,no. death is not ready for you yet.
上帝对你另有安排
God has something else in mind
否则如何解释你可侥幸逃脱的神奇之处
or how else could explain the miracle of your survival?
我的兄弟 蒙塔古勋爵给我发来一函
My brother, Lord Montague, send me a letter
给我看看
oh, show me.
随函致上我主及我的祝福
I send you God blessing and mine
虽然希望安抚你却最终难抑悲伤
although my try to comfort you has turned sorrow
罗马教廷对你青睐的主要原因让人不可思议
it is increditly to me that by the reason of brief sent to you by the bishop of Rome
你将在那里与其度过这个冬季
you should reside there with him this winter.
如果你执意如此 那么我便失去所有希望
if you keep that way,then fearwell all my hopes,
但愿上帝能够解救你的母亲和家人
and may God save you mother and all your family
我该怎么办
What I shoudl do?
那信件绝非出自你兄弟的手笔
That letter was not written by your brother,
而是由克伦威尔口述迫使而就
but dictated to him by Cromwell,
这是魔鬼的信息
that is messenger of Satan
永远不要让罪恶蒙蔽了你
never let the Devil beget you
不管其威胁还是允诺
either with his threats or his promises.
你灵魂的代价是永恒的高洁
The price of your spirit is eternal virtuousness
一旦你背离你的主
if once you let down your guard,
魔鬼立刻附体占据你的口舌
the devil will sleep like a scivvy into your mouth.
从此魔鬼将永远让你为他代言
And forever afterwards he will speak for you.
大主教大人
My Lord Bishop.
你与你的委员会被要求审核
You and your commitee were ask to examine
统一英国教会基本教义
and determine the doctrine of the Church of England.
但是看来你们未就任何事情达成一致
But you seems not agreed on anything.
陛下
Your Majesty
目前委员会成员仍有
they coutinuce to be some fundamental
一些基本理论上的分歧
theological differences between the members of the committee
我很了解
I'm aware of that
但我越发失去耐心
But I's growing very impatient
也将不容忍任何分歧
and I would not tolerant any more divisions
我起草了6项基本教义问题
I have formulated six fundamental doctrine questions
这六项问题的解答将成为我们的信仰之本
The answers to these questions will form the basis of our faith.
当然 全凭陛下定夺
of cause, As Your Majesty's wishes.
我得再去坎特伯雷与大主教协商此事
I shall go once to Canterbury in consult with the Archbishop.
大人 不必舟车劳顿
My Lord, save yourself to the journey
我相信我们彼此非常理解
I think we understand each other very well.
就让克朗默大主教管好其自家花园罢了
Let's leave archbishop Cranmer to attends his own garden.
此事不必去烦扰他了
There is no need to bother him.
你同意吗
Don't you agree?
陛下 此乃英国教会
Yours Majesty, here are six articles of faith,
之六项基本教义条款
upon which Your Majesty Church of England
- 英国教会将据此而确立 - 请朗读
- is to be built and sustained - Read them
第一条款事关上帝圣餐的变体的事实
The first article concerns the truth of the transubstantiation of God.
藉著饼与酒的被祝圣
by the consecration of the bread and wine during Holy Mass ,
饼的整个实体被转变成为
it takes place a change in whole substance of the bread
我主基督身体的实体
into the substance of body of Christ Our Lord,
酒的整个实体被转变成为祂宝血的实体
and a change in the substance of the wine, into substance of his blood.
否认此条款的处罚为火刑处死
The penalty for deny this is death by burning.
即使是事后认可也不饶恕
Even after recantation
第二条款事关圣体圣事
And the second article concerns that with holiness
的神圣唯一性
of cup from eliaty during comnunion
是故如果我们再提供圣血
or if we offer them the blood of Christ that will lose
它将失去圣事的尊严
all their reverence for the Holy Sacrement
宝血的效力将消失殆尽
and the power of blood would be washed away.
天主呀 我们恳求你屈尊就卑
Quam oblationem quaesumus you Deus
为我们变成你的爱子
ut nobis Corpus et Sanguis fiat
我们的主耶稣基督的圣体及圣血
dilectissimi filii tui.
第三条款事关所有教士
The third Article prescribe the continuity legitimacy
修女当独身守节的誓言持续有效
of the vows of celibacy for all priests and nun
圣保罗曾言道
Perhaps does St.Paul not say:
没有娶妻的
He that is without a wife,
是为主的事挂虑 想怎样叫主喜悦
is solicitous for the things of the Lord, how he may please God.
娶了妻的 是为世上的事挂虑
he that is with a wife, is solicitous for the things of the world,
所以已婚之神父
All priests who are now married must forth face desire their wife
如不愿放弃妻子者 罪罚至死
or face the penalty of death
第四条款事关神职人员誓言之纯洁性
The fourth article concerns the observation of the vows of chastity
教士誓言应纯洁无暇
A priest makes vows of chastity
任何玷污视同教会大恶
and any violation of such vows must surely be a sin against the religion.
违背对上帝之誓言
To turn a vows to God
犯奸作科
and to rise the pityful formunication
如此自愿追随魔鬼奔向地狱
is to follow the devil willing into the mouth of hell
请你们接受 大家吃著这个食粮
Accipite et manducate ex hoc omnes:
因为这就是我的身体
Hoc est enim Corpus meum,
第五条款事关决定继续为亡者做弥撒
The fifth article here decided, it concerns the continuation of private masses
籍此诚信者可得我主
whereby,good Christian people, may receive both
对其灵魂神圣美好抚慰与祝福
godly and goodly consolation and blessing for their souls.
基督圣体
Corpus Christi.
第六条款事关私人告解之重要
The sixth article confirms the importance of the confession
你们要彼此认罪 互相代求
"Confitemini alterutrum peccata vestra "
彼此认罪
Confess your sins to one anothers
基督圣血
Sanguinis Christi
任何对上述六条款之争议
anyone who dispute against these articles
将被视为异教徒
that is now considered a heretice
如同目前国土泛滥的极端分子路德之流
like those extremist luteran now role this land
违者处罚至死刑 绞刑 淹死 分尸
The punish for trasgression is to be dead by hanging,drawing,quartering
并罚没收财产
as well as forfeit of its states and property
任何试图逃避新条款实施者
Any man who decides try to flee England
视同叛国罪
in face these new articles considered to committed treason
按叛国罪同等罚罪 严惩不贷
and suffer accordingly the awful fate, handed out to traitors
谢谢 主教大人们
Thanks, my Lord Bishop.
祝贺诸位红衣主教大人的辛劳与大智大慧
Yours Eminence ought to be congratulated on your hard work,and manifest wisdom.
我们得以拥有六条款指路明灯
Here we have six articles with idea we may clear anxious.
尚有最后一款补充
There is one final amendment.
自即日起 掌玺大臣须重填主祷文如下内容
Henceforth the Lord Privy Seal would be alter to conclude the doxology.
因为国度 权柄 荣耀 都是祢的
For thine is the kingdom, The power and glory
阿门
Amen
勋爵大人们 红衣主教们 公爵大人
My Lords, Eminence,Your Grace,
现在条款已定
Now that these matters have been determined
让我们即刻全然实施
Let's procedure with absolute diligence
摧毁一切所有冥顽不化妄图阻挠者
all those who stubbornly standing against us
这不是六条款 而是六记连环鞭
these arenot six articles, they are Whip with Six Strings
克朗默不得不把他的太太和儿子送回德国
Cranmer have to send his wife and son back to Germany
否则就得被火刑烧死
or be burnt
远非如此 瑞奇先生
well, It is not just that, Mr. Rich.
亡人弥撒 私人告解 圣餐宝血均为天主教规范
Private Mass,the confession, the body and the blood of Christ! These are catholic measures
他已复辟 这是终止改革的信号
He is rooling back the reforms, it is the end of our reformation
为什么呢
why
因为在他内心深处他一直都是纯正的天主教徒
"Because in his heart he has always been a true Catholic,
只是除了一件事 就是他不允许无论是教皇
except in this one thing: That he will have neither Pope,
还是路德 或其他任何人居于他之上
nor Luther, nor any other man set above him